Never forget why you are the church.
God is good.
If you were to turn your Bibles to Romans chapter 11, Romans chapter 11.
This morning, we're gonna kind of go off a little bit
from the, uh, from the study that we've been doing.
We're within the study, but we're
gonna do a necessary clarification here this morning.
I do want to say this as well.
I understand that not everyone is not here.
It's not because they slept in.
I know a lot of people are traveling.
It is spring break.
And so we do want to pray for safe travels.
As a matter of fact, pray for me and my family.
We are traveling with the Lebanon baseball team.
Uh, after church today to go to their spring,
uh, spring break tournament and Gulf Shores, and so I'll be able to bring
devotions and and preach to the kids, uh, throughout the week.
And so just pray for me to have a word, and from
God, to be able to share with them.
And so, but I just, this morning, we're gonna do
a clarification that is very important.
There's something that can be easily misunderstood
in Romans 11.
And sometimes we can read scriptures and get confused,
and instead of digging deeper,
We simply just kind of roll on into
our time of reading.
And I believe that is why there is so much biblical illiteracy in
the church today because we don't wrestle with the text.
You understand what I'm saying?
We do not wrestle with the text.
We are satisfied with what we have been taught,
so we never learn anything else.
Church, if you don't know more about God today.
Then when you gave your life to Christ, then
you are not digging deep enough in his word.
Amen.
See, we started Paul's letter to Rome, February of last year.
Think about that for a second.
Now, we've had a few breaks in between chapters and miniseries
here, miniseries there, but for the most part, we have
taken each week and dedicated it to Romans.
This is a marathon, not a sprint.
I was watching an ad about an app that gave you a
verse every hour on your lock screen.
And man, people were raving about how, man, it's just getting God's word into
my life, and I don't have to worry about it, and I
don't have to change anything, because I look at my phone all the time.
So it's just right there.
Listen, that's not it.
You understand what I'm saying?
Y'all with me this morning?
It's going to be a long morning.
That how it's going to be.
Listen, we don't need more things to
keep us from God's word.
We need things in our life.
We need discipline in our life to get us more into God's word.
Now I'm not saying as a supplemental resource, you can't
have something on your phone that pops up a scripture every hour.
But what I'm saying is we have a culture that is dependent
on that, and in doing so, as claims scripture
out of context, and it's not the truth, and
that is a dangerous place to be.
See, we have done a great job of decreasing
our time with the Lord.
A verse, an hour, sounds great to a devotional 3 minute
read driven society.
But we've got to get deep into the words so the word can become deep into us.
Amen.
As a matter of fact, the Bible says this in Psalm 119, 11.
Thy word have I hid in my heart that I might not sin against thee.
Well, man, the church has just as much sin and as the world does.
You know why?
Because too often the church is in God's word as much as the world is.
They aren't.
Listen, I am privileged and burdened
and very glad and joyful that you trust me every single Sunday
to stand behind this pulpit and preach to you God's word.
I would not want to do anything else in life.
I wouldn't want to be anywhere else, but see the Grow Baptist Church doing exactly what I'm doing.
Amen?
I just want you to know that.
But this is not enough.
You've got to, you've got to dig deep for yourself.
You've got to know God's word for you.
Listen, hey, I'm just a man.
I study so I don't mess up, but can I tell
you some of the things I've learned as a kid?
I have learned as I wrestle with a text that that's not really what the Bible says.
And that makes us uncomfortable.
Amen.
Like you're uncomfortable right now.
So this morning, I want to look at an important doctrine that can be derived in Romans 11.
It's a doctrine that has been dividing lines of denominations for many years.
It is a doctrine that has been debated for 1000s of years.
It is a doctrine that is central to our Christian faith.
We talk about differing tears of doctrinal importance.
That is what we can and cannot disagree on.
I believe eternal security is a doctrine that holds
much significance on how we walk and view
our faith in Christ.
It's more than an Armenian versus Calvinist debate.
The question of, can you lose your salvation
is a big question to answer?
Now, why does Roman stir this question up?
Because nowhere in Romans does it say, hey, this is the question that we're asking.
So look at the scripture that we looked at last week.
Look in Romans chapter 11, starting in verse 19.
if you're there, say read.
That wilt say then the branches were broken off,
that I might be grafted in.
Well, because of unbelief, they were broken off and now
standest by faith, be not high-minded, but fear.
But if God spare not the natural branches,
take heed lest he also spare not thee.
Behold, therefore, the goodness and severity of God on
them which fell severity, but toward thee, goodness, if thou
continue in his goodness otherwise, thou also shalt
be cut off.
What does it mean to be cut off?
Is Paul preaching that one can be saved and then
not due to unfaithfulness?
That is what we're going to look at this morning.
The title is very simple, a necessary clarification,
a necessary clarification.
Let's pray, Father, I just ask you, Lord, to give me clarity.
on this this morning.
That allow me to preach of power and liberty.
And God, I pray that I let your word speak, God, for you.
So Lord, I pray that you just open our hearts to your truth.
In Jesus' name, pray.
Amen.
To understand this, we must 1st understand saying what
happens at salvation.
Gaining salvation is a miraculous event
in our life that serves as the foundation of a faithful life to God.
Amen.
But to lose salvation, hear me.
To lose salvation would have to be just as miraculous.
Are y'all not with me this morning?
That's okay.
Listen, hey, to lose, to gain salvation is
a miraculous event in someone's life.
Would you agree?
I mean, you're taken from death to life.
Amen, if you're saved, someone get excited about it.
You know what I'm saying?
But to lose salvation would be just as
miraculous.
What is a Christian?
A Christian is not someone who has simply
walked an aisle, filled out a card where has been raised in church.
All these things are not bad, of course, but they
are not what makes someone a Christian.
A Christian is someone who has placed their faith and trust in Jesus'
Lord and savior, and in doing so has the indwelling of the Holy Spirit.
Nothing else can be a true definition of Christian.
Listen, do not let the world define
what following Christ looks like for you.
I understand people love when celebrities
get up there and say, oh, I love Jesus and this and that and we
love jelly roll this and all the athletes.
Let me just tell you something.
Do not be deceived and be aware.
I tell you what, I tell you who I admire in the faith.
Those who are doing it day in, day out,
even in the struggle, even in the suffering, living their life for Jesus.
Amen?
Not just getting on a mic, renting an award and saying the name of Jesus.
I'm talking about those who are living for Christ.
I have more faith in a believer that's
a door greeter every Sunday than somebody at the Grammys saying, thank you, Jesus.
But either way, A Christian is someone
who has placed their faith and trust in Jesus' Lord.
So we got to look at, to answer this question, listen,
I understand some of you might disagree with that, and that's okay.
We're going to look at what happens when you're saved.
What happens when one becomes saved?
First, the Bible says we are made a new creation.
Look at 2 Corinthians 5.17.
Therefore, if any man be in Christ, he is a new creature.
All things are passed away.
Behold, all things are become new.
Have you ever heard someone say, when I get my life cleaned up, I become a Christian?
Or I just got a few things to handle
before I can come to Christ or where I'm not going to go.
I just go, whoa.
I think a bug is trying to kill me.
Let me get some water.
Woo, someone say help him, Lord.
I almost just died for real.
But it's okay, 'cause I'm saying it's all good.
But listen, people say, well, I'm not gonna come to church
until A, B, and C.
And I hear it all the time.
Man, it breaks my heart because that's not how it works.
See, this is exposing a tragic lack of understanding
about salvation.
Now, I want to say this, and I said this to the Wednesday night crowd,
change is not a requirement to be saved.
It is a result of being saved.
Change is not a requirement to be saved.
It is a result of being being saved.
When we place our faith in Christ, something supernatural happens.
We are made, according to scripture, God's
holy word, a new creation.
Listen, this new creation is not an improved creation.
It is fully and completely new.
So many people are deceived because they
make moral adjustments in their life, and they feel like,
okay, now I'm right with Christ.
Listen, if you're someone who struggles with alcohol
and you drink about one beer less a day and
call that, well, I'm closer to Christ, that's not what we're talking about here.
If you struggle with lust and doing things that you shouldn't do.
And you say, well, I don't do it as much as I used to do it.
That you might have improved in the world's eyes,
but that's not what we're talking about here.
The Bible says a new creation.
The old creation, the old things are passed away.
This is a spiritual transformation.
Jesus and John 3 calls it being born again.
There's no better way to describe salvation than a new birth.
What is so beautiful about a new birth?
It brings new life.
Spiritually, when a person is not saved, they are loving
or living in the old things, that is the sinful nature, the works of the flesh.
This old man, listen, this old man cannot be revived
because the old man is dead already, according to Ephesians
chapter 2, verse one, and you have he quickened who
were dead in trespasses and sins.
So when we place our faith in Jesus,
this transformation from death to life results in God making us
a brand new creation.
We are born again.
Now don't miss this.
That term passed away in 2nd Corinthians 5.17.
Look at it again at the verse.
Therefore, if any man be in Christ, he is a new creature.
Old things are passed away, behold all things are become new.
This phrase brings a meaning of ceasing to exist.
Look at the verse in the next verse in 2 Corinthians
chapter 5, verse 16.
Wherefore, henceforth, know we know man after the flesh,
yea, though we have known Christ after the flesh, yet now henceforth,
know we him, know more.
Jesus used this exact phrase, speaking about his
word in Matthew 24, verse 35.
heaven and earth shall pass away.
But my words shall not pass away.
See, we see here the same phrase to explain 2 different realities.
The current heaven and earth will pass away.
That is to cease to exist.
It'll be no more.
Revelations 21, verse one says, and I saw a
new heaven, and a new earth, the 1st heaven, and
the 1st earth were passed away, and there
was no more sea.
That is a ceasing of existence.
But the word of God will never pass away.
In other words, it'll never cease to exist.
We see this proclaimed in the Old Testament.
Isaiah chapter 40, verse 8, the grass withereth.
The flower fadeth, but the word of our God shall stand
forever.
Amen.
We see it clearly proclaimed in the New Testament, 1st
Peter 125.
But the word of the Lord endureth forever.
And this is the word which by the gospel is preached unto you.
Now, what does this have to do what we call eternal security?
Look one more time.
Therefore, if any man be in Christ, he's a new creature.
Old things have passed away.
behold, all things are become new.
For us to lose our salvation.
Hear me.
God would have to destroy the new creation.
And put to life the old creation.
Nowhere in scripture can you find any evidence or teaching that this is how God's work.
It is contrary to his will and plan.
Now, I want you to understand something here.
I am not going to be able to hit every single thing that
has to do with eternal security or the arguments against it.
As a matter of fact, this is a two part message.
You're not gonna get all the answers till next week.
Okay?
That's just gonna have to be how it is.
But I do want you to know, we cannot look at anything
but the whole view of scripture and what God promises.
We cannot take one little thing and say, well,
this is how we're gonna make a theological foundation.
We have to understand that when God does something, he does it.
When God says you're a new creation,
That means you are made new.
The old things are passed away.
As a matter of fact, the Bible says, the old man is crucified in the flesh.
We were made a new creation.
By the way, we should be excited about that.
You are not who you are.
You are not who you once was.
Secondly, when a person gets saved, not
only are they made a new creation, but we are redeemed.
First Peter one, verse 18 through 19 says
this, for as much as ye know that you were not redeemed with
corruptible things, as silver and gold from your vain conversation
received by tradition from your fathers, but with the
precious blood of Christ, as of a lamb without blemish and without spot.
The practice and doctrine of redemption, it goes all the
way back to the Old Testament.
We see it in God delivering his people in Exodus
chapter 6, verse 6, wherefore saying to the children of
Israel, I am the Lord.
And I'll bring you out from under the burdens of the Egyptians, and
I will rid you out of their bondage, and I will redeem you with
a stretched out arm and with great judgments.
We see this spoken about by the Psalmist in Psalm 7715.
Thou, thou hast with thine arm redeemed
thy people, the sons of Jacob and Joseph, say li.
See, God delivered his people from the bondage
and the danger of Egyptian captivity.
But it's more than just deliverance.
It's also a transaction.
In the Old Testament.
There was something called a kinsman redeemer.
We see this displayed in the book of Ruth.
Listen, if you haven't read the book of Ruth, you need to go read the book of Ruth.
an absolute, amazing book of the Bible.
Ruth had no husband.
Her husband had died in that time.
Listen, that puts you in a very bad situation as a woman.
She had no land, she had no earthly hope.
She had no protector.
So under the council of Naomi, her mother-in-law, she presented
herself to a man named Boaz, who was the next of kin.
Boa has accepted the role responsibility
of kinsman redeemer.
How he did this was he bought the land her
husband left behind and took Ruth as his wife.
He took her at a great price.
That changed everything for Ruth.
As a matter of fact, it changed everything so much that if you
go down the line, you get you get David,
King David out of their lineage.
In other words, God, because of the kinsman Redeemer, Ruth
went from having nothing and no hope to everything that the Redeemer could offer.
It changed everything.
It was a transaction.
What does that have to do with us?
The Bible makes it clear that salvation is a spiritual transformation, absolutely.
But it's also a pricey transaction.
Jesus acts as our kinsman redeemer.
Ruth, the reason why God put Ruth in the Word
of God is to look forward to Christ.
See, see, Boaz was a type of Christ in
regards of kinsman, redeemer.
He did so by dying on a cross for our sins.
1 Corinthians chapter 6, starting in verse 19.
What?
Know ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy Ghost which
is in you, which ye have of God, and you are not your own,
for you are bought with a price.
Therefore, glorify God in your body and in your spirit,
which are gods.
For us to lose our salvation.
God would have to revoke his purchase.
There is nowhere in scripture that gives evidence or teaches that God would
ever evoke the purchase of those who have been saved.
Think about Judas.
He sold out Jesus for 30 pieces of silver.
The legal price for a slave to be compensated or a
slave owner to be compensated, if the slave was gored
by an ox, was 30 pieces of silver.
In other words, that was not a lot of money.
When he realized how bad he was mistaken in betraying Christ.
He went back to the chief priest to return the silver.
They refused to accept it.
Wow.
Because it was blood money.
Listen, church, if those corrupt priests refuse to take what they deemed
blood money, how much more so will God refuse to revoke the precious and
perfect blood of Jesus Christ that saved us and bought us?
This purchase, praise God as non-refundable.
So next, when a person becomes saved,
We are justified.
Look back, we studied this in Romans chapter 5, verse one, it says
this, therefore, being justified by faith.
We have peace with God through our Lord, Jesus Christ.
Now, this is one that gets good right here.
To be justified, is to be pronounced righteous by God.
Someone who is lost, is legally guilty before God.
Your sin is clear and obvious.
It's an indictment against you.
When you are lost, you are guilty.
Because God is holy, he is the only righteous judge.
Therefore, for one to be guilty before him is
to deserve eternal condemnation because he
is holy, he must separate from that sin.
This is a guilty state that we cannot work our way out of.
We must be pardoned.
In order for us to be pardoned.
Jesus had to shed his blood at Calvary.
Ephesians chapter one, verse 7 speaks on this, in
whom we have redemption through his blood, the forgiveness of sins,
according to the riches of his grace.
This is taught also in the Old Testament, Micah
7, verse 18, who is a godlike unto thee,
that pardoneth iniquity and passeth by
the transgression of the remnant of his heritage.
He retaineth not his anger forever because he delighteth
in mercy.
That word pardon literally means to
lift, carry, or to take.
Now stay with me here.
Because of our sin, we are guilty before God.
Amen.
There is nothing we can do to lighten the sentence or
work our way out of condemnation.
We are in the righteous judges' hands.
When we become saved, the blood of Jesus, the Bible says covers us.
That's the atonement.
That's the covering from the blood of Jesus.
The Bible teaches that we are washed and cleansed
from our sin and unrighteousness.
Because the righteous judge sees the blood of Jesus on our account,
he pardons or enlists the guilty sentence away
from us, and we are declared and legally pronounced
righteous in the eyes of God.
In other terms,
We are set free from the penalty of sin.
Romans 8.one.
There is therefore now no condemnation to them which are in Christ
Jesus who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit.
There's a song that I think goes along with this so good,
and it's called not guilty.
And it goes like this.
I stand accused.
There's a list a mile long of
all my sins, of
everything that I've done wrong.
I'm so ashamed.
There's nowhere left for me to hide.
This is the day.
I must answer for my life.
My fate is in the judge's head.
But then he turns to me and says,
Listen to this.
I know you.
I love you.
I gave my life
to save you.
Love, paid the price
for mercy.
My verdict, not guilty.
How can it be?
I can't begin to comprehend what
kind of grace would
take the place of all my sin.
I stand in awe.
Now that I have been set free.
And the tears were loved.
as I look at that cross
Cause it should have been me.
My fate was in the nail
scarred hands.
He stretched him out for me and said,
I know you.
I love you.
I gave my life
to save you.
Love paid the price
for mercy my verdict.
Not guilty.
Church, when he pronounces us righteous.
That's all there is to it.
Amen.
Listen, we're not guilty.
We have heard of a presidential pardon, amen?
Did you know that a presidential pardon are irrevocable,
and they are final?
When God pardons someone, it is fine.
For us to lose our salvation.
God would have to revoke an irrevocable sentence of righteousness.
That's not all.
Not only is all that true, but we are promised eternal life.
John 316.
For God so loved the world that he gave his only begotten son, that
whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have everlasting life.
First John 225.
And this is the promise that he hath promised us even eternal life.
First John 5.13.
These things have I written unto you that believe in the name of the Son of
God, that you may know that ye have eternal life and
that ye may believe on the name of the Son of God.
I want us to think about this today.
Those who place their faith and trust in Jesus is Lord and Savior, this
is those who confess him as Lord with their lips and believe in their heart.
God raised him from the dead.
We are talking about those who are saved.
In that moment of spiritual transformation,
you are made a new creation, you are redeemed, you are justified.
All these things are final, and what is the result?
You are promised eternal life.
Hebrew 618 that by 2 immutable things
in which it was impossible for God to lie.
We might have a strong consolation.
That's a comfort, who have fled for refuge to lay hold upon
the hope set before us.
In other words, because God does not lie.
We can lay upon, lay hold of the hope of Jesus Christ.
Hebrews 1023.
Let us hold fast the profession of our faith without wavering.
Why and how?
For he is faithful, that promised.
Church for us to lose salvation.
God would have to break his promise of eternal
life for us.
That is impossible according to scripture.
Now, Next week, we're going to go over another couple
of reasons why our salvation is securing Christ.
But this morning I want to ask you something.
Are you saved this morning?
I mean, I want you to really think about it for a second.
Because see, what happens is we try to put all these
things on our salvation.
We try to, well, if I do this, and if
I do that, and if I stay doing this, then God will
keep me, let me just tell you something.
I have fallen in a trap of if I don't pray enough, if I don't
read enough, then somehow God's going to punish me.
That is not the relationship that we are to have with the Heavenly Father.
When I'm raising my kids, I don't want them stepping
on eggshells thinking that one wrong mistake, and I'm going to
just kick them out of the house, but then they can get right, and then I'll bring
them back in the house, and then one more wrong mistake, and I got to kick them out
of the house, and then they get back right.
Listen, that's not how salvation works for us.
Are you saved?
Every single one of these reasons for eternal security results in a changed life.
You say, well, and I'm going to just give you a little tidbit for next week.
Well, preacher, what about those people that say they're
saved, but they're not living like they're saved?
Well, the Bible has a word for them too.
You know them by their fruit.
Well, what about those people that go to church their entire life?
And then they they they leave the church and and
and they they never come back and announce Christ, but the word has
a word for that too.
Well, they were never of us because they didn't continue with us.
I don't know about you, but when I gave my life to Christ, when
I had the end drawn, the Holy Spirit, everything changed for me.
I can't go back to what I was because I'm a new creation.
I may struggle with the flesh.
I may fall and stumble every now and again, but I am desiring
to pursue Christ in my life.
What we've done in our culture is we've allowed sin
so much in the church that we blurred the lines on,
well, we live for Christ or we don't know.
Listen, it's either you obey.
Bible says, if you love me, keep my commandments.
That's what Jesus says.
If you don't do that, do you love them?
We cannot be any of these things we've talked about without there being a difference
made because of Jesus.
And if you are saved, are you living in the freedom and peace that is eternal security?
that God gives you in your life.
What hezbound eyes closed over this place this morning.
I want to...